Phil: The individuals we support, very
often, routine is a big thing and the need
for a routine and a lack of routine would
result in dysregulation and be a trigger
for you know, coming off of baselines
and escalating into crisis  points.
Having a, I mentioned earlier, using
the teach approach, having visual
schedules, very clear what's happening
at this point and what's coming
next,  and who is supporting as well.
So who's going to be working
with me at this point.
So you can see that predictability.
Zoe: Children that have struggled
with processing routines.
They struggled with understanding
when they came into school,
what they needed to do.
And we really supported them mainly
through visual timetables, visual guides
and schedules so that they had a way of
referring back to the visual schedule
and working out what they needed to do.
Kerry: A young person I support really
struggles with a sense of time and that
time moves on and that things run out.
And when I first started supporting them,
they could spend all day eating breakfast.
There was a visual schedule in place.
The classroom around them was moving on.
But because that there was, yeah, they
just didn't have that sense of time
moves forward and there's an urgency
to some of the things that we do, so we
did a lot of support at home and we've
done a lot of support in school and what
we found works for them in particular,
in this occasion, especially around
eating, not so much for other tasks,
but we have a traffic light timer.
So we used a visual traffic light timer
where they can't see the time countdown,
but it's green for about 70% of the time.
And then it goes amber
for 85% of the time.
And then it and will
flash red  at the end.
Phil: I mean, I work with a couple
of young people at the minute and
they have no real concept of time.
They might be able to...
they can tell you the time from the clock.
But for instance, you could say
this will happen in five minutes.
They can tell you, oh, that will be
a 4:29, 5 minutes from now, but the
concept of, you know, even what a
minute is, is difficult to understand.
So having that structure, that routine,
the visual schedule that helps at
least sort of cope with, or give some
understanding of, you know, time in the
chronological sort of linear fashion.
Zoe T: Probably fair to say that
most people with autism would have
difficulty processing information
and would need more processing time.
And so...
what you do with that is just give them
more processing time and potentially
sort of prompts them if you can.
Yeah, the question about
routines, I think is more about
unpredictability and uncertainty.
And my answer to that one would be
that you try to support the person
with autism to master the developmental
milestones that they need to master
in order to manage uncertainty and
unpredictability for themselves.